it's incredibly nice to be in your country.
Unfortunately our cultures and
our languages are so different that it's
impossible to get their feelings for
your languages probably you cannot get
my feelings to my original language.
My... my native language is Italia is Italian
and I can present myself in a few words
in in my language,
"Buonasera, lo sono Italo Vignoli."
So this is how my language moves and it's
so different from yours, but I think what
makes free open source software unique
is that it can do together different
cultures and different background in a
way that is absolutely transparent.
Yesterday, at the dinner, we had people
from at least two three continents and
we have people from several countries
and there was no feeling of difference
between us and that I think is the end
of different religions because we have
the Muslims we have Christians we have
Buddhists from and probably others that
they don't know from from Asia but
there's no real barrier between
ourselves. So it's I'm proud to be
speaking here I hope it won't be the
last time that someone from let's call
it the core of TDF will visit your
country you're warmly invited to visit
Europe when possible and when you do
that drop us a line who will be happy to
show the best of Europe.
This is not a touristic...I think.
And I just want to start with a with a few maps.
Many people know that
my background is in geography, I'm a
geographer so and I'm in technology and
software just by chance. In addition to
the fact that they don't take
geographers and you have to get a salary
at the end of the month. So, I start with
a few maps, maps that some people have
already seen that will show you what the
lack of investment in open source
software have created in term of
unbalance in the world. So, this is the
typical map that you everyone knows
where each country is represented by the
surface. So, of course, Japan is similar in
in surface is a little bit bigger but
this is my country that is Japan is a
little bigger but not that much.
if we switch to population, you see that Japan
is a lot bigger than Italy, because there
are more Japanese than Italian, but for
instance look at India, look at China, how
big they are because the number of
people is there, and look at how smaller
in South America, how small is Canada,
that is a huge country.
And let's go to something that is interesting for us.
it's export of software licenses. Okay.
So you have a big one which I will not
didn't we don't even tell the name
because everyone knows that.
This is Ireland, Ireland in Europe is kind of a bridge
between the States and Europe, so all
large European corps or large American
corporation have an office in Ireland
that import their software and then
export the software to all of Europe
because I am honest very low taxes.
You think that this is what is this bubble.
This is Suriname. Suriname is a very tiny
country in South America that has the
same function of Ireland for South
America, so it's a it's a it's a former
Dutch - colony where taxes are 4%.
So of course, Microsoft and Oracle they they
ship to Suriname and from Suriname
to ship to the other countries in
South America.
So, this is really unbalance see where Africa is.
See whereall your countries are. I mean it's like
you're disappearing from, from the world,
and, and this is unfortunately this is an
unfortunate situation. It's not because
we want America's not works for software
but we would like to have a more
balanced situation. And now look at the
import. So the import is exactly the
opposite you can check out Japan is big,
look at our Italy is big, Ireland is big
because they import a lot of software to
export a lot of software, and, I can show
you where the United States are. The United
States are are one pixel line between Mexico and Canada.
So they basically they don't exist in term of
import of software licenses, and let's
just think and imagine how the work
would be different if there was more
free software which is usually developed
locally or if not entirely developed
locally is partially done locally.
So this is something that when we started
the project. So this is is our paper
plane this is we started in 2010 and
said we have a dream in 2020. We will
like to have 200 million users, and we
would like to have made a dent in the
software industry. We... I think we have met
it we have already reached by according we
estimated the target, but we still behind
in in our idealistic objective.
We have a heritage of 10 years of OpenOffice many of
the people that have founded the
LibreOffice project were active in the
OpenOffice community.
I know that in Japan
some people were active but some have
left or are not active anymore, but the
idea when we started was to build on
very strong history we have a strong background.
OpenOffice was born in 1984
if you look at back at history when
Marco Börries created released it the first product
and so it's we have almost 30 and close
to 40 years of history behind us.
OpenOffice was started in the year 2000 and
then in the history of the project there
are some some issues that were then
tackled and solved by LibreOffice.
For instance, this is OpenOffice in 2000,
year 2000, so this is the basically the
code and the repositories and in 2005
probably in a number we developed as
they a lot of fun stuff so OpenOffice
was like this was a little bit fat and
in 2006, at the Lyon conference, there was
a presentation by the OpenOffice guide
and they said "okay, we understand that
the community is not act in some area, so
we will reduce code complexity" not done
done by LibreOffice. We will improve
patch handling at the time there was the
famous patch from Kouhei Yoshida that
sat for 28 months before being merged.
so apostasy in in a branch for 28 months is
something that is really unacceptable.
Luckily the patch was so advanced that
after 28 months it was still good, but 28
months are one generation in technology.
Then, mentoring newbies and this is
something that with LibreOffice we have
managed to do. So, go quickly through
the history in 2009 Oracle acquires Sun,
the people in the community were already
a little behind
how Sun was managing the situation,
so the... we quickly decided that it was the
right time to fork to do something to
renew what the it was impossible to
manage that, and we try to be to do this,
so OpenOffice was here and the reality
that at that time was the risk of
abandonment by Oracle was huge, and we
were right when we said that it was
abandoned so we have mostly been LibreOffice
and you know that LibreOffice today
as as a record of development and
releases over close to 10 years we have
regularly release a major release twice
a year via the regularly minor release
every month, month and a half, so product
is maintained regularly, and we had in in
my religion they had a "last supper" and
that that was not a likely situation so
we we prefer to say that we are the
"first supper" was in Budapest, September 2, 2010.
These are basically the people that founded
the the project there were a few others that were
already around the project, for instance,
the notary is one of them, but these are
the guys that really discussed how to
put together the the new the new project.
You may know some of them, this is Florian Effenberger, this is Chris Nowak, he is
the guy that choose green as the color
the crease of the design, then he had a
baby, he changed his work so he left
project, but his contribution was
fundamental. Charles Schulz from France,
he is still around. Kendy, or Jan Holešovský,
Kendy is a lot simpler. Thorsten Behrens,
Michael Meeks, Caolán McNamara,
this is me, Sophie, I don't remember his
name is... anyway was one he changed work
as well after and (....) yeah, exactly. Cor Nouws,
Olivier Hallot, and Leif Lodahl from Copenhagen.
So we... we were
the guys that did the fork. And so we
created this was the announcement and we
say you know we have the target in 2000..
2020, which is nice it's next year.
o we are nine year on the road.
And these are then the history these are the forks so
you know that,
then there is Apache OpenOffice,
the unfortunate story of IBM choosing a
competitive product with a with a free
software product but corporation do not,
at least in Europe, I don't know how it
is in Japan, but at least in Europe and
the United States, the corporation do not
like community, and they especially do
not like community members as me.
I'm very straightforward when I am if I
think that you're doing something wrong
I tell you that you are doing something
wrong so I repeatedly told Sun during
the previous years that they were doing
something wrong and they didn't really
appreciate as much my transparency.
So, we will revert the paradigm.
This is OpenOffice. A company that
protects the project. So it's like but
when it rains, if you are under the
umbrella you you don't get wet, if you
are outside the umbrella you get wet.
we will revert to the umbrella this is the
concept of the mixing bowl. So in in the
United States, they say that if you could
hold ingredients of a salad then you
miss them very well, the salad is better.
So it's as a better flavor. At least
in in my country, we say that we jump on
our own on a boat and we have everyone
has to row in the same direction
probably something similar in other
European countries, I don't know which
kind of metaphor you use in Asia, but the
concept is simple. This is the community
that decides and where to go and
everyone is empowered to provide this contribution.
This was the home page,
the first home page and the founding
principle are: copyleft license, we use
now we went from LGPL to MPL.
No contributor agreement, based on
meritocracy, governance by the community,
and independence from... from vendors.
In.. in our status not and in the board of
director there cannot be more than 30% of votes
from representative of a single company.
And we went, when we launched
many people saw our project like a kind
of protest against Oracle,
it was not a protest
against Oracle, it was a project to build
something new, we were something... there
was an article on you can say that we
were the strikers so we want you to
strike against Oracle, no that's
completely wrong we want you to promote
free software, user freedom, document
freedom, open standard, set. Of course
develop LibreOffice. Then we have added
another project that is the document
liberation that is the project that takes care
of filters to import and export documents.
And these are the numbers, so we have 206 members we have
and... by the way, I know that in the
audience today there are there is people
that is not yet TDF members and so I
expect by the end of next week,
we'll see applications of all the people
that are not in TDF member and sitting here,
I'm a close friend of the president
of the Membership Committee
we is Italian as well is name is
Gabriele Ponzo, so I will tell about
Gabriele tell me who has sent the
application, who has not send the application,
we know where you be...
and this is not really,
but but take it seriously.
And, our main assets are developers,
we don't have many many developers from Asia,
I hope there will be more there are some.
Thank you for your work because developers are
precious without developers the
completed project, because there won't be
a product because the reality is that we
have a fantastic product that gives us
the opportunity of not only being here
and talk between us but also good
governments and
governments and be proud of what we
proposed to governments because we have
a product that is able to replace any
proprietary software with an advantage
for the people that use it.
This is the number of developers.
if you look at the the dark green is the old developers so
that those that were already a project,
but as you can see this is from 2010 to
end of 2016 then we stopped counting
them because there are so many that it
doesn't make you know at first there was
the the the criticism from some that
said all they will not attract
developers there will miss developers so
we we don't like developers this is the reality.
After we were at close to 1200
developers committing to the problem we
said we stopped counting them, because it
doesn't make any sense. What we wanted to
show it was readiness in this chart and
what are doing developers we have a core
of 40 paid or unpaid but mostly paid by
companies that do the more solid work.
We have a number of regulars and some of
the developers that are in this room are
the regulars, they do a very important work,
and then we have occasionals but
occasionals that replace it them each
other every year, so at the end, we have
around 300 developers on on a yearly basis,
which means that the product has a
very solid background.
And, these are commits this year in 2019.
As you can see, of course,
there are Saturdays, Sundays,
vacations for people, but it's a rather
solid this is just before the
announcement of LibreOffice 6.2.
that was so, of course, there is a spike of activities
around announcements.
And these are contribution by organization.
So, many developers are employed by companies,
so the this is the patches from Collabora,
these are from Red Hat, unknown is not a
nice way to say volunteers would be
better volunteers, but as they come they
are not backed by a company they weaken
we use the word unknown, then there is
CIB, TDF are people employed by TDF,
and then there are small chance done by
by others, but what is important to see
in this slide is that we don't there is
not one single company or group doing
more than 50%, that would put the project
and a reason because if the 50% goes
away then the rest of the project will
be not be able to keep the project alive.
And we are our six... our fourth development cycle, we started at 3.3 and
that was called cleaning,
then 4 was code refactoring, so we redeveloped what
was already in the product but was not
really optimized. Then we work at the
user interface we still work at the user
interface but the reality is that we at
six, we have productivity although we are
not active with the mobile application,
but LibreOffice is the only free office
suite that it's running of every
platform, so it means that is running on
Windows, macOS, Linux, the cloud and
mobile. The only one that gets closed
because misses only Linux is Microsoft
Office but all the other means
the mobile or something in in the other
so they don't have a cloud version and
LibreOffice online that will be their
have been talks today, and it's very
important, of course, we have to explain
to people that we we give the engine the
enabling technology, we don't provide
infrastructure, simply because the
infrastructure as a cost that is impossible
to stand for a not-for-profit foundation.
And we do a massively well quality.
So we use Coverity scan which is
a weekly service that allows us to clean
the code, we use OSS-Fuzz from Google,
we use all the tools that are available to
improve the quality of the code.
If you look at the numbers if you look at the
Coverity scan reports, LibreOffice is
probably the productivity software with
the lowest number of issues for one
thousand lines of code. We are well below
names like Firefox, we are well below
names like Thunderbird from Yuma which
are considered very stable software.
This means that, of course, it doesn't
mean that we are bug-free software,
bug-free software does not existent, but we
have a very solid foundation for the code.
And of course, the community is as
developers are strong asset the
community is the second one because if
you don't have developers you don't have
the product, but if you don't have the
community you don't have language
versions, you don't have promotion in
the local
market so the community's fantastic.
And is something that we should all be
proud of being part of.
And this is the community, in sorry Nigeria is missing
but I will add immediately. it's
impossible to know all the places where
we are present this is in some cases our
best guesses based on information that
we can get from the network.
Of course, Africa is is one of the top priorities
for the.. for the foundation, because we
know that there is a lot of need for
software in the in the continent and the
problem is that it's probably difficult
in term of culture to explain some some
realities, but as you know as you see the
communities, in in all over the Americas
in Central America's I I think we have a
community that there's no evidence like
in in some other countries, but in Asia
we are almost in in in any country and
it's important to develop where we don't
see a community and it's important to
develop the community in countries where
the community is not to the level of as
in other countries, for instance, we were
discussing about how to raise the
community in India, and I think that
China's well is it's important.
Luckily we have Chinese speaking people
in the community they are Taiwanese but
they speak the same language,
so of course this can help a lot because you
we have already a basis for the Chinese community.
India I think is a complex
country because it's so big, so many
people, they have many local languages so
it's a difficult one. In... in addition to
this in being at these conferences for
us is so important, because we learn a
lot on how the community works outside
our original community so Europe is such
a small if you look this is the entire
continent is a smaller than China's
moral dimension is probably smaller than
Australia. And this is a is a continent
so of course in in Europe where the
project was born community is really
looks alike in every country the
differences are really minor apart from
languages. But differences were in the
way you develop the community are very
small. While the community works in
different ways in your geographies just
because we have very strong but very
different cultures and we respect all
the cultures I was in Indonesia last
year and I think that the Indonesians
have done a wonderful work in growing
the community, they started two years and
a half three years ago but now they have
a community as is self-sustaining, they
are organizing events local events, they
are attracting more people because of
course in a community you have people
that come in go and you cannot back on
the fact that people is staying here forever.
And this is the activity of the community
these are
just to give you, this is the core, these
are the regular people, and these are the
casual people, this is based just on the
commit or the number of emails that are
sent this is the dashboard of the
document foundation you can access it at
the dashboard.documentfoundation.org.
So you can check it for
yourself and you can filter the data
to see according to your interests.
And of course, last asset is LibreOffice,
open source software is is now adopted by the
majority but still we have to do a lot
to make people aware about open source
software. If we look at Google Trends
LibreOffice is this one, so this at last 12
months, Brazil is the country
where most research are coming from, but
of course, if we look at the more details
this is very general is Google Trends so
it's based on searche,s but if we look at
other measurement methods for instance,
in in Asia
you see Japan having probably the larger
share
and I will show the the slide about Asia
in a few minutes.
User base estimate, as I said we are
estimating around 200 million users, so
this is more or less how we estimate the
number, so there are between 2 and 3
billion users, PC users, we say that we
have 100 percent of Desktop Linux, maybe
it's not 100 that is 99.9.
We have 10% of desktop Windows,
10 percent of desktop macOS, so if you
sum all the figure is 236 million and
we say, okay we are conservative, we say
we have 200 million is probably 100
million are unique users, the other 100
million are using also another software
so they may be using Microsoft Office or
other office suites or other specific
software.
We provide two versions fresh versus still
we deliberately do not use
the word stable, because the reality is
that they are both stable, but they need
let's say that one is newer than the
other or if you want the Still is the
more tested by users, of course when we
suggest which version to use, we usually
suggest the older one, not because not
because the newer one creates issues, but
because you never know who are the users
so it's better to start with a more
tested version and then if necessary
move to the next one, but instead of the
opposite.
And this is more or less gives you the numbers,
remember that LibreOffice is still we have LTS options.
so there are two companies they are both sitting
on the advisory board, they provide the LTS
version so if you meet a government or
corporation
that wants to get a product that is
optimized for their need, they are not
getting a better product, they get a
brother that is optimized, so they have
support they have back porting of
patches, for instance, we... we do not back
port patches over nine months so when
when the software is nine month old you
you don't get any any security patch any more.
While on LTS version, you
get security patches back ported forfive years.
So let's say that you could
update the software after five years,
instead of doing it every six nine months.
That can be an issue in some
cases.
This is LibreOffice Online Writer,
this is LibreOffice Online Calc.
They work... they work amazingly well they're
solid and they save ODF
and ODF is important.
What can we do in the future.
In the future we can together, but
only we do that together we can really
build a global ecosystem and
contributing means sharing it's we are
all, and let me make a note about the
language here. Unfortunately we don't
speak the same language all over the
world. This is in one sense a pity
because we have communication issues but
the beauty because each language
represents our culture. So we are forced
to use English as a kind of global
language, English is not my native
language, I'm a decent English speaker
but English is not my native language.
With my wife, she's there,
mystic Italian we don't speak English
within ourselves. So I totally understand
and the effort that you make looking how
you've run your language. The effort that
you make it's amazing to speak English
that is based on our Western way of
writing, so we are amazed by the fact
that you are managed to speak such a
line of language, but don't be shy.
We want to, if you know three words of
English, use those three words of English.
We want to understand you. Don't don't
consider English as a barrier. It is not.
if necessary it's that to do signs, we
Italians are very good at dancing on the
floor, so the same, because that you're
communicating is more important than
judging the others on language skills.
And let's look at a few numbers on Asia.
So this... this is the visits to the download page.
I can give you this is two other
but this is important because it's visits
to download page, so these are the continent.
As you can see, Europe is still
quite high, Asia is still is divided in
East Asia, Central Asia. We have to
improve because still Europe and North
America are still they have they rely on share.
These are from Asia area
so you have East Asia, Central Asia, South
Asia, Southeast Asia, and Western Asia.
Of course, this probably tells you a lot
more than what it tells to me because
you know the reality of your continent.
And these are the countries. Of course I
have to create an others because there
is a very long tail of countries, but yes,
India, then after Japan and Indonesia then
you have China, Turkey, Philippines, Taiwan
Thailand, South Korea, Saudi Arabia,
Malaysia, Hong Kong, Vietnam, Pakistan,
Singapore, Israel and the other one are 6%.
As you can see, there are
unbalance in term of so this does not
reflect them the potential number of
users of your countries, of course and
people see Japan here but Japan has one
tenth of the inhabitants of India, so India
should have a lot more downloads than Japan,
nothing mean don't stop downloading you
let's have the Indians increasing the
downloads
And that's like what this guy,
because I am an old man, so most of the
times I'm the oldest thing in in the
building I don't know if I'm the oldest
here because I'm not able to judge you
as I would be able to judge a European
but I'm 65 so I don't think there are
many younger people than me and I think
"you're never
too old to have another goal and to
dream a new dream," so I want to stay here
for years again to help younger people
to grow up in the community, I think that
it's very important for someone that has
experience to transfer the experience to
the younger people. So my dream is, this
is FOSS today, this is people that know
free and open-source software these are
those that use, but they in many case
they use but they don't know, for
instance, many use VLC on their mobile
phones and they don't think is free
software. And these are the people that
refuse, and my dream is tomorrow to say
these are people that know these are the
people that use and these are the people
that refuse this mean we cannot get rid
of those unfortunately, and that's all
for my part of the speech, and there is
Lothar now that will add a few important
remarks about certification how to build
a business also around LibreOffice.
So, thank you very much.
Before i introduce myself, I think so tropical I want to
tell you that I have all three
challenges, the first one is it's my
first stay in Asia in my life, and I'm
very wanted to be here in the LibreOffice Conference Asia,
and the second
one is it's also the first time in my
life that I present my presentation and
have used to to presentation before my
wife, so please be kind with touch nervous.
And the third one is to speak after
Italo, it's... it's a challenge, it's a
challenge because he's so so good in
making presentations and I won't stress
you too much I will hurry up a little
bit to join the six o'clock.
So, first of all, let's have a look a little bit on
the business side,
I want to speak a little bit about certifying
as a LibreOffice professional,
and why this is a win-win-win situation
for the community,
and perhaps that we have a few words to myself,
this is all formal stuff
that as Italo mentioned
the history of StarOffice and OpenOffice,
My company .riess applications was the
first migration partner of some in
Europe so we have done the first one of
the first migration project in the early
2000s it was 2001 or something about this that
we have worked[?]
together with the staff of Sun and spoke
with them about how can we bring OpenOffice, StarOffice then OpenOffice
to professional users as the deployment
in an professional environment.
And this is now 7 or 8 years we have changed the
product LibreOffice, so this is the
track records I have in business with an
allowance open opposite[?] LibreOffice.
So, let me focus on the community and I
wanted to bring in a part of the
community in which is not always
recognized but which we all know that it
is a very important part of the
community,
it's the third group of stakeholder it's
the eco systems around the product we have.
the first group first for most all
users around them, they are private, they
are professional, even if they use LibreOffice offline as we know everybody and
the new ones since few years Online, and
prefers Online their first times, and the
second one is the computer team, often
spoke about the community, it's the
participants to develop the product
so everybody who brings in some
contributions to the product is a man
that we speak with community, yes,
also the ecosystem which is needed to
guarantee the support the professional
support and services for these professional
environments what we want to discuss.
So, as we start conversation for thinking
about business, thinking about business
in was in Asia, there wasn't the question
how do we get business around LibreOffice,
is it like the genesis from dust coming out,
perhaps Italo is saying "bang!" and
there are some big migration projects to
be progress with professional
deployments and checking who doing
this ecosystem and everything is
fine for the next hundreds of years.
No, we all know I don't want to to have any
religious feelings by that we all know and
this is not the kind or the way it will happen.
So what could be the way it pretends? and
this is what I want to mention in this
talk what brings LibreOffice and some
kind of community, some kind of ecosystems, some kind of projects...
to a very wise one where we have chicken,
we have egg, and
growing up more and more over the time,
and the question is what are the
catalysts, what are the criterias, to
grow that up to have a vital ecosystem
around LibreOffice.
As I recap my slides, this
morning I was a little bit concerned
about this slide. Because, to bring in, here in
Asia, the role model of Europe in this
case Germany,
I felt a little bit that this is
misplaced. Why? Well, ecosystem with and
around LibreOffice is services. it's most
part services support and what we
discovered the last last two days is
that the cultural services here in Asia
as a lot higher and better and that we
have in Europe, so I'm feeling a little
bit concerned to bringing this example
how how it can works, but perhaps we can
take the catalysts I've marked them in
green, LibreOffice green, color which are the
cafeterias which I think could be
catalysts for bringing up more
business world.
So let's have a look at what has
happened in Germany. There were some
anchor persons and some local community
there which starts doing some business.
So it's all about you and me ,there
must be some person who say "yes, we do it,"
and that's very very important.
In the German case, little mentioned some names,
Thomas Jacqueline, Florian, as well as Thorsten,
and our persons. [???] enough or not enough[?],
an anchor company who care about
the products, it was in the early stage
StarDivision, afterwards it was Sun, I
have talked with Michael Bemmer around these, all these community issues,
see it as good or bad, catalysts
that was good anchor companies want to make business with them.
Third one, the lighthouse projects. Not
many projects, but I remember that in the
early 2000s, I was talking to the
city of Munich about the whole migration
to Linux and this stage of OpenOffice, and
that it's rather the years that they
decide to do that. So some lighthouse
projects are important that other which
are thinking about to migrate see that
there are some role models for it.
Especially in our case of public has
administration's who were thinking about
turning away from Microsoft Office to LibreOffice, and
why did then because there was a
depression in the ecosystem. There was
somewhere a cost sensitivity, which we
heard in all over topside works, today
the cost sensitive all about license
costs, awareness about vender lock-in,
with long consequences also costs
arguments.
And the way to support Open Document Format, technical issue to come to to
peel the side of this vendor lock-in. So
this this were catalysts there were some
people as mentions besides Sun who
want to make business bridge who some
services support for for the software
and afterwards
we developed these certifying process
for acknowledge some companies, some
people and these companies that they do
a qualified service for this product.
And this is the only thing, the only thing
you see the others become you can check
for for Asia, I think there are some
anchor persons here the rule for Asia who
are promoting this product like Franklin,
like Shinji here in Japan, like Alice,
sorry to be not mentioned everybody, but
there are anchor persons and the local
community, who is couple of do that. I think collect some anchor
companies, awesome lighthouse projects as
as CTC from Taiwan, Fans from
Indonesia and of us we heard today which
are it could be the lighthouse projects
as catalyst is here to the ecosystem in Asia.
I don't know if there is something
like a kind of depression in Asia, but I
know and you have mentioned in the talks
there's a costs
and the sensitivity from the lock-in
issue in Asia, so what we can do from Europe
or from all the community, the ecosystem
community could help you at least certification.
Let me give just short
introduction to this certifying
LibreOffice certifying proces.
If it were interesting I tell you that we have
tomorrow these business workshops and
registration so asked me questions about
that tomorrow that I is become an accent
explain the whole process in this few
minutes but just a few words.
There are four profiles for... we think
four profiles for certifying.
There are professional certified developers,
there are professional migration consultants, theer are trainers, professional trainers, with the own profiles,
and perhaps somewhere in the future
we will have an own profile for
certified supports consultants, but we
cover this supports profile I think a
part of the migration and the
part of the trainer skills.
And this is... these are the profiles about the kind of
process to get certified . The profile of
development is levels slightly different
the other two. Developers are invited by
the engineering steering committee so
they are recognized for giving
contributions to the source code and if
you have done some of these
contributions they recognize you as a
developer who can master the code, and
then you will be invited and if you want
to be listed as certified developer, and
if you say yes you will be listed.
Quite different is the certification for
migration and training to be sure in the
process we certify people, not companies,
and as a consultant for migration or as
a trainer you should have some
experience in this area for training or
for migrating to LibreOffice, then you
should show these experience, for example
with some documents, to the committee
applicate to to this certifying role,
with these documents and it will be
reviewed by the committee and if it is
acknowledged that it seems to be like
little bit experienced in this area, you
get divided to do such a registration
which we are doing tomorrow here... and if
the committee of reviewers, normally
three or four, all of these committees and yes
we trust these quality of service of
this person who gets certified.
So why it is chocolates[?], why is this
helping, why is this a win-win-win-win
in the community from the stakeholders.
So I think it's easy to
understand out of the customer side of a
professional user side, it's good to have
suction such contracts such a list you
if you need such a certified service
where you can have contact persons where
you have you can ask and you know that
they are used with trust from the
community. So mainly the customer, the
users are gaining the quality of
services some of these certification.
The community everybody who is in the
contribution truth. Typical win element is that we get out of
these certified people certainly and
I believe us how we can develop the product
heads, especially ahead in in the way for
using it in professional environments.
Integration issues, compatibility issues,
and so on.
And the third poem that win is typically
for applicants, because
you ask certified people listed in
an official list of TDF, on LibreOffice online
websites, where everybody can see that
you are certified migrator, certified trainer,
or something like this.
And certainly the witness working in such an awesome community, we enjoy with you.
So... Doumo Arigato!
Okay, it's six o'clock so I mean if you have questions
and take part tomorrow come to me come
to Italo and we will help you with this.
Thank you very much!